<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proposals for national banks whereby the profirs on usury, to reduc'd to three per cent. per annum, will supply his Majesty more plentifully than ever to carry on the war, exempt the nation from land taxes, great customs and excises, exceedingly promote trade and navigation, and give England many other very large advantages.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828747</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828747</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56032)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1957:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proposals for national banks whereby the profirs on usury, to reduc'd to three per cent. per annum, will supply his Majesty more plentifully than ever to carry on the war, exempt the nation from land taxes, great customs and excises, exceedingly promote trade and navigation, and give England many other very large advantages.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression with corrections and additions.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and sold by Peter Parker at the Leg and Star over against the Royal Exchange in Corn-hill, and John Waltho at the Cloysters in the Temple, and John Gouge at the Castle in Westminster-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Domini MDCXCVI. [1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33178:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33178:1"/>
            <p>PROPOSALS FOR National Banks; <hi>Whereby the Profits on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, tho reduc'd to Three</hi> per Cent. per Annum, <hi>will ſupply his Majeſty more plentifully than ever to carry on the War, exempt the Nation from Land Taxes, great Cuſtoms and Exciſes, exceedingly promote Trade and Navigation, and give</hi> England <hi>many other very large Advantages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Impreſſion with Corrections and Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and Sold by <hi>Peter Parker</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> and <hi>John Waltho</hi> at the <hi>Cloyſters</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>John Gouge</hi> at the <hi>Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Hall, Anno Domini</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33178:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33178:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROPOSALS FOR National Banks;</hi> Whereby the Profits on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, tho' reduc'd to Three <hi>per Cent. per Annum.</hi> will ſupply his Majeſty more plentifully than ever to carry on the War, exempt the Nation from Land Taxes, great Cuſtoms and Exciſes, exceedingly promote Trade and Navigation, and give <hi>England</hi> many other very large Advantages.</head>
            <p>THREE Manuſcripts have been lately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ſome Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, which having met with no diſlike ſave of being too prolix, 'tis prayed that Objection may atone for the preſent Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; And this being penn'd in too much haſt, 'tis hoped the honeſty of the Deſign will excuſe that alſo.</p>
            <p>The Subject was of Banks, ſuch as entirely tend to the common good of the King and the People of <hi>England;</hi> and which are of a Nature widely different from thoſe other Banks that aim Chiefly at the further enriching a ſmall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33178:3"/>number of ſharpwitted Purſe-Men, at the coſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which will be yet more impoveriſhed by their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing the vaſt profits on the Uſury of the Nation into their own Coffers.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore humbly propoſed, that one <hi>General truly National Bank,</hi> be eſtabliſhed in <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Governour and Directors to be (from year to year) nominated by Parliament; And at the ſame time that Banks be erected in every Ward <hi>therein,</hi> and in every other City, and Market Town in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and thoſe to receive Rules from the Head-Bank in <hi>London,</hi> and thither to return Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts every Week, all which are every whit as practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable as the Offices of the Cuſtom's, Exciſe, or any other, and may be ſettled and put into Action ſooner than were, or can be, thoſe Banks now on Foot; becauſe no time need be ſpent in taking Subſcriptions (Funds enough to the full be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing already provided) not other Terms be made for Mony brought in, or to put Bills in circulation; for that the great Conveniencies and Eaſe in Commerce which thoſe will give all over the Nation, will cauſe them to run (every where) ſwift of themſelves, without the charge of one Peny <hi>per Cent.</hi> to quicken their Rotation. Nor will other Banks longer give it, than as Sugar-Plums at firſt to ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Men's Entrance, for 'twill be ſo far from needful, as that Bank-Bills in <hi>Holland</hi> are (at this very Day) in higher eſteem than their beſt Money in Baggs by 4 or 5 <hi>per Cent.</hi> And in <hi>Venice</hi> by 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> as is remark'd by Mr. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> in the 17th. Page of his Book on the ſubject of new coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Mony; Printed in <hi>Anno</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>A plain Scheam for the regular and ſafe Proceedings of which manifold true National Banks in <hi>England</hi> without any confuſion, and to render falſe or ſtoln Bills uſeleſs to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or Robbers is providing to be preſented, whenſoever a proper ſeaſon ſhall admit for its Acceptance.</p>
            <p>Moreover (which is worthy to be very ſeriouſly obſerved) theſe Banks may be crected without difficulty, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon agreement of the Inhabitants themſelves in any Cities
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33178:3"/>Towns, Hundreds, Villages, or Neighbourhoods in the Counties, and by holding Correſpondencies with the Gold-ſmiths or Banks in <hi>London,</hi> plentiful Mediums of Trade will (at the ſame inſtant) ſtart up like Bleſſing unexpected, and render the Commerce of every ſuch place, as brisk and more ſecure and eaſy, than ever it has been, without three Pence in Money beſides for pocket occaſions; and the neat Profits of theſe Banks at but 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt <hi>per Annum.</hi> will defray a great part, if not the whole, of the Taxes Exciſes and other charges of thoſe parts where the ſame ſhall be put in uſe.</p>
            <p>The Advantages of eſtabliſhing Banks in the Methods here mentioned will be mighty and numerous, many of which are (perhaps) as yet undiſcerned; But it will be ſufficient to name theſe few following, which ſeem to be the moſt obvious, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Theſe Banks will furniſh the King with ſeveral Millions of Money, <hi>per Annum.</hi> without burthening the People, and will redeem all the Funds that can be redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and diſcharge both the Intereſt and Annuities of thoſe that are not redeemable, and will ſatisfy all Bills that ſhall be drawn by the Treaſury, and return back the Intereſt again into the Service of the Nation, if theſe free natured Banks may but have the firſt offers of thoſe Bills.</item>
               <item>II. Theſe will and all debates about the bad Money, and ſet the People at eaſe.</item>
               <item>III. Theſe will repair the loſſes by Guineys, and bring li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral profit to the Nation thereby.</item>
               <item>IV. Theſe will advance the Eſtates of the Orphans.</item>
               <item>V. Theſe will be ſafe Repoſitories for private mens Caſh.</item>
               <item>VI. Theſe will return the multitudes of ſums great and ſmall, to and from place to place, throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, without charges of carriage or dangers of Robberie.</item>
               <item>VII. Theſe will quickly call back that great (or rather greateſt) part of the Money in the Land, that is now em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in Uſury, and convert it into Trade.</item>
               <item>VIII. Theſe Banks will defray (in great part, if not all, or more than all,) the expences of the War, and other the Charges of the Kingdom.</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33178:4"/>
               <item>IX. Theſe will take off the neceſſity of great Land Taxes, Cuſtoms or Exciſes, and make all Commodities cheap.</item>
               <item>X. Theſe will raiſe Lands and Houſes to more than double the preſent Values.</item>
               <item>XI. Theſe will unite the Intereſts of the landed and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd Gentry, and capacitate the former, and excite the latter to contribute towards the ſpeedy retrievement of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, and to carry on that, and all other Trades, to ſo great degrees, as to render <hi>England</hi> (by thoſe means and by its happy ſcituation and excellent harbours) the chief Storehouſe and Bank of <hi>Europe,</hi> or rather, of the Univerſe.</item>
               <item>XII. Theſe will exceedingly augment our Navigation.</item>
               <item>XIII. Theſe will give handſom Entertainments of buſineſs to many Gentlemen's Sons all over the Land.</item>
               <item>XIV. Theſe will employ and cauſe to be employ'd all the Poor that are able for any ſervice,</item>
               <item>XV. Theſe Banks will procure the beſt prices for Cloth and other the Productions and Manufactures, Native and Foreign.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> As to the firſt Advantage, that will accrue, if <hi>Regular Methods</hi> are concerted, theſe Banks will have (in all likelyhood) more than a ſufficiency of Money, freely, and ſpeedily brought in, to pay unto His Majeſties uſe, all the ſums that the Parliament hath given, with caſh in Specie, to thoſe that ſhall deſire it; which none will do in great ſums, unleſs it be (through envy) to be lodged in their Coffers, or elſe to melt down, or tranſport 'em, becauſe Bills even from any Banks are (every day) experienced, to be much more Eligible in Payments than Gold or Silver in kind; Nay tho it be of the new Coin, yet 'tis not ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Receivers, as Bank Bills; which <hi>Holland</hi> with <hi>Venice,</hi> and all parts where Banks are, do effectually prove; Much more will theſe pleaſe in the Countrey (where are troubles of Carriage, and dangers of Robbers) as ſoon as ever theſe Bills ſhall there come in uſe; and 'tis further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that (in a very ſhort time) theſe Banks will be able to redeem all the Funds that can be redeem'd, and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33178:4"/>the Kingdom from payments of all Intereſt whatſoever, as will be by and by made more plain.</p>
            <p>Which <hi>Regular Methods,</hi> to ſtock the Kingdoms true ſort of right National Banks with plenty of Caſh in Specie, are humbly propoſed to be, as followeth. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> That all his Majeſties preſent Revenues, and Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es be paid into the Banks, next adjacent, to the places where the ſame ſhall be collected.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> That all the remaining bad Money be brought into the Banks neareſt to the dwellings of the Owners, on, or before certain days (for that purpoſe) to be aſſigned, and Bills iſſued for the ſame; and likewiſe, that the new Coin be there returned in, ready to be delivered at the call of thoſe it belongs to, who (in the mean time) having Bank Bills, the Commerce will be plentifully furniſhed with a full and ſufficient Medium of Trade, and there will be no occaſion at all of the ill Coin's longer currency which would be avoided, leaſt evil Men convert all they can of that new Money into ſuch (as 'tis ſaid) is now and ('tis juſtly feared) will be buiſily proſecuted as long as they have proſpect to utter it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> If the Guineys are brought into the Banks, on ſhort notice before more can be imported, and Bills given for the ſame at 22 <hi>s.</hi> (which never need go higher than to prevent their Exportation) and as much more as each Bringer in ſhall ſwear they have (without Fraud Covin or Combination) taken thoſe at to 30.28.26. <hi>s. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe will ſtore the Banks with Caſh ſo very plentifully, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly, as to render the ſaid Banks able (beſides furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His Majeſties occaſions at demand) to lend (immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately) ſo much Money on Mortgages and depoſited goods, as that the profits at 3 <hi>per Cent. per Annum.</hi> paid quarterly for the Bills in Rotation, by the help of that Fund, will (in a ſhort time) reimburſe the loſſes made good by the Guineys, and become a ſtanding income thence forward to the Nation; which will be liberally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed without injury to any particular Man, and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33178:5"/>greivances of our Induſtrious, and Honeſt Tenants Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and all Loſers by Guineys be redreſſed, to the general Satisfaction and Joy of the People.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly.</hi> If the Orphans Money be brought into ſuch of theſe Banks, as the Truſtees ſhall chuſe for that purpoſe, and Intereſt to be paid for it, or elſe, the ſame to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd in ſtocks of Trade, as the Parliament ſhall direct; this will advance the Eſtates of the Orphans, and alſo augment the Bank's Caſh, and thereby enable them the better to ſupply His Majeſty, and the ſooner to iſſue the more Bills in Circulations.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly.</hi> Theſe Banks will be much ſafer Repoſitories for private Mens Caſh, than the hands of fickle Gold-ſmiths or Scriveners in the City, or of hazardous friends, either in Town or in the Country, if the Kingdom be ſecurity for the Banks, as will be a great deal of reaſon it ſhould, when all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt on the wheelings of the ſaid Bills, ſhall be applyed to the ſervice thereof, and then this will be another expedient for largely increaſing the Caſh in all the Banks, and enabling them to circulate the bigger multitude of Bills. And here muſt be remembred, that if any diſaſters by Fire or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſhall happen to any of the Banks, the ſame to be made good by all the Banks in the Land; And likewiſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any Money may chance to be wanting, that Defect to be ſupplied by the next Banks moſt convenient.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly.</hi> The great number of Men whoſe occaſions will daily oblige 'em, to return Mony from place to place, will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly chuſe to pay their Mony into that Bank next at hand, and take out Bank Bills of Exchange, for the ſame which they may carry, or ſend to thoſe Banks, (howſoever remote,) where their Correſpondent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inhabit, or themſelves or their Agents ſhall travel, all over the Realm; rather than to be at the troubles, and expences of carriage, and to run the riſques of Robbers; whereby much Caſh will flow into all the Banks in the Land, and the conveniency of Bills to be had from thoſe Banks where the ſame muſt be paid, will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Receivers rather to exchange thoſe for other Bills,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33178:5"/>than to deſire Caſh in Specie, eſpecially in caſes of great ſums, as is daily experienced at the Banks in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>None will imagine, that theſe ſix ways in conjunction, can fail to ſtock the Banks with a ſufficiency of Money, to be conſtantly lodg'd in them ready (at all times) for His Majeſty's Services, and to pay off ſuch Bills in Specie, as ſhall ſo be deſired; Yet for further ſecurity, If, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Head-bank in <hi>London,</hi> have power to borrow Money upon ſome Parliamentary Fund, as that of <hi>Salt</hi> or any other, to be ſetled for the more viſible ſecurity of the Lenders, to take place one year hence or at other fit time; 'Twill put all beyond queſtion, which Money will ſoon be repaid will the Intereſt, nay and without ever requiring one Peny from that Fund; Howbeit the ſame may be provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Reſerve, for the more ſure ſatisfaction to the ſaid Lenders; For it cannot well be doubted, but that leſs than twelve months experience of the profits of 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> on the Bills, in Rotation from all the Banks in the Kingdom, will remove all ſcruples for ever. And in the <hi>Second</hi> place if Bank-Bills are made current by Law, but only until the end of the next Seſſions of Parliament, all objections will be anſwer'd, and no man prejudiced one Groat.</p>
            <p>Yet of theſe two Collateral Reſerves, 'tis not (at all) probable, there will be any occaſion, tho too much care cannot be taken in a matter ſo great; for 'tis not likely that of the Caſh which comes into the Banks, ſo much as one Tenth part will be called for out again in ſpecie; as is proved by thoſe Banks already in uſe, much leſs will it be ſo deſired out in kind, where Men dwell at diſtances from their Markets and places of Commerce.</p>
            <p>Six of the firſt mentioned Poſitions, being ſuppoſed to be ſufficiently proved, the Seventh is moſt plain, <hi>viz.</hi> That if Uſury on Mortgages, and depoſited Goods (not meaning on Perſonal Securities) other than from theſe Banks be ſuppreſt, and be there reduced to 3 <hi>per Cent. per Annum.</hi> the Uſurers will forthwith turn their Money into Trade, or other wholſom uſes, and give Employments to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33178:6"/>the poor, and ſo take off a great part of that charge by them; which Intereſts are now at 5 or 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and are made up 8 or 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> to the Borrowers, by their long journeys, with the Scriveners Fees, and Perquiſites, whereby many worthy Families have been brought to lack Bread; and tho the Intereſt ſhould be leſs at the Banks in <hi>London,</hi> yet the tedious journys thither, and charges there, and in clearing up of Titles far from Home, would make thoſe at ſo great diſtance not much helpful or eaſy to Gentlemen, or others afar off, either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Wales.</hi> But rather the quite contrary in divers regards; becauſe the Banks in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> will draw up the Money from the Countrey, and leave there no Medium for Commerce, and which will tend ſo very much to the prejudice of the Nation, as that all the Families therein muſt (of neceſſity) become their Tributaries, even from the Palaces to the Cottages and Alms-houſes, not the Sick nor the Impotent, no nor Infants excepted; ſeeing all muſt uſe <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Earthen-Ware, &amp;c.</hi> And all this to ſerve the turn's of a few avaritious Perſons who have already great part of the Caſh of the Realm in their Hands, which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the vaſt Profits on their Paper-Money will ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them to encroach yet further than is proper to be expreſt; which huge and mighty Profits do of right belong to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the publick, and who ought not to be thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd by the ſiniſter Contrivances and crafty Devices of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous ſelf-ſeeking Men, and the generality of the Kingdom be thereby made poor and miſerable to Perpetuity.</p>
            <p>For the Annuities the perpetual Intereſts and Charges in Collections are computed, will (this very year) riſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Million of Money, which is one Tenth part of the Rents, and is at leaſt one half part of the Land Tax, how much more ſoever thoſe may augment from Year to Year; All which theſe Banks (if now were eſtabliſh'd) would pay off in one Years time, ſo far as the Laws will admit to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd, and would (at the ſame time) disburthen the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Remainder; But if things ſtill go on at the rate that they have done, Every Day will ſwell the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33178:6"/>Kingdoms Debts bigger, and harder to be paid, and the ſtate of the Nation will grow worſe, and worſe, and from Year to Year further off from Proſpect of Retrievement, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a perpetual Enthralment under Debt to the Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Natives, and Foreigners; as have been for abundance of Years paſt, and are at this very Day the unfortunate (if not for ever inſuperable) Circumſtances of thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Kingdoms and Countries of <hi>Spain;</hi> whoſe Shackles of Uſury that Immenſneſs of Treaſure, tho flowing in every Year from their Fountains in <hi>America,</hi> hath not been able to get looſ; ſo unimaginably ſtrong and powerfully guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are the Fetters of high Uſury wherever thoſe are got faſtn'd on the publick; Nor is it often that private Perſons once deeply entangled therein, have found any better.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Debts of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are ſaid were contracted by reaſon of their embroilments in Wars, for more than an hundred Years paſt, and 'tis not yet heard of, that any part of that principal is hitherto paid, or that they are able to pay it, neither is it by the. Creditors deſir'd; becauſe the Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they receive are profits much larger, ſafer, and eaſier, than they can make by any other improvements of their Money; and who being in thoſe times (a great part) Aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens (chiefly <hi>Genoueſes</hi>) are ſince then become Naturalized <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and link'd in with the Money-monger Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, (too many whereof were then concern'd in their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) and twiſted together with them into the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Poſts of thoſe Realms, ſo as to ſway the Councils of thoſe haraſs'd Kingdoms and Dominions; to purſue and protect all poſſible Advantages to their Uſury, whatſoever becomes of their Trade and Navigation, which all know is fled from them, and their People live idle, poor, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and are a Prey to every Aſſailant, and like to be ſo as long as their Nation endures; of which abundant more might be ſaid, but this will ſuffice, becauſe 'tis agreed on all hands that the Sloathfulneſs, Poverty, and Miſery of thoſe ſo extreamly much decayed Kingdoms of that once moſt flouriſhing and powerful Monarch, and Terror to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33178:7"/>Chriſtendom, is owing to the vaſt Sums of Money continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuckt from that Crown for Uſury by their <hi>Dons Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does &amp;c..</hi> to the ſo great vexation and Calamity of that Indigent Common People under intolerable Gabels, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Exciſes) as produced that tragical and moſt deplorable Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Naples,</hi> under the Fiſherman <hi>Thomaſo Aniello</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1647. Written by a Gentleman who was an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs thereof, and may be a ſeaſonable warning piece, it being not certain whether the Common-People of <hi>England</hi> would contentedly bear things of this nature ſo long.</p>
            <p>This Tragical Subject of <hi>Spain,</hi> brings to mind the <hi>Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum</hi> of <hi>Horace,</hi> for tho <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſeem now in the very ſame Road of running the like ſad and woful Fate, if the Fore-ſight and Subtilty of our ſelf-ended Banks ſhall prevail with any of our Honourable Parliament Members, who (perhaps fee not the mighty ſelf-ends theſe Gentlemen reach at) to be drawn into their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties hoping by the help of them and their Friends to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on and uphold their Uſury Projects, taking theſe politick Purſemen of <hi>Spain</hi> for their Precedent; yet if alſo on the contrary part, the great Wiſedom of our King, and of our every way diſintereſted good Parliament Patriots, Men fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſs, (ſuch as 'tis hoped are the moſt part of that Honourable Houſe) ſhall but vouchſafe to eſtabliſh this communicative ſort of true friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Banks, theſe would immediately diſſipate all thoſe black Clouds that at preſent impend, of our Kingdom's future Calamities by now plunging into the like Debts as miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Spain</hi> hath done; and would be mightily advantagious to all the Families and People of <hi>England;</hi> the rich and the Tradeſ-men would be eas'd in their Taxes of all ſorts, and having Banks in the next Market Towns would enjoy the ſame benefits thereby, as thoſe who dwell in and about <hi>L<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>odon,</hi> and both rich and poor will have all Commodities cheap. Oh! That the different Natures of theſe comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cheriſhing and ſo mightily profitable to the publick laſt mention'd Banks of the one ſide, and thoſe canker-like co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33178:7"/>ones (to our Nation) now on Foot of the other hand; were but ſedately conſider'd, and their quite oppoſite effects but rightly diſtinguiſhed, all Arguments would ſtreight be at end, and our Land be deliver'd from its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſtreſſes, and be happy and glorious to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>For proof of the Eighth Poſition, the Intereſt at 3 <hi>per Cent. per Annum</hi> (according to modeſt Computation) will bring after all charges paid neat into the Banks upon the huge multitude of Bills that will be always in Rotation upon Mortgages, depoſited Goods, and ſuch ſubſtantial per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Securities as the Banks ſhall approve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, much more than ſix Millions of Money <hi>per Annum;</hi> but whatſoever that ſhall amount to (more or leſs) the ſame will defray (in great part, if not all or more than all) the expence of the Wars, and other the charges of the Kingdom; yet as to perſonal Securities, the inferiour Banks may be limited, not to lend above one Thouſand Pounds to any one Perſon, without the approbation of the Head Bank in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Ninth Poſition, when as all, or great part of The Nations Expences ſhall be diſcharg'd by the Intereſt coming into theſe Banks; Land Taxes, Cuſtoms, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes will need to be but very low, if not quite be laid down, and when Peace ſhall come, and thereby the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall not lack thoſe large Supplies of Money which the ſaid 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> will be found to bring in, that Intereſt may then likewiſe fall ſo much lower, as to raiſe no more than the neceſſary Charge of the Nation ſhall require.</p>
            <p>For the Tenth. The values of Lands are accounted to riſe or fall according to the rates of Intereſt, which being now by Law at 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Land commonly goes at 20 Years purchaſe, and when Intereſts ſhall fall to 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> land will by conſequence riſe to 40 years purchaſ; but about <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Somerſet ſhire</hi> and thoſe parts where Regiſters are kept, Lands are ſaid to go now at 30 Years purchaſe; And (when the one half part of the preſent Intereſt ſhall ſink) may poſſibly riſe to 60 Years purchaſe, which tho
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33178:8"/>is a rate too hgih to be expected yet when Landed Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall have Money at cheap' Intereſt near Home, to pay off the Debts of their Anceſtors, the portions of younger Brothers and Siſters, and ſometimes their own Debts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in younger years; they'l need not, nor will they, part with one foot of their Patrimonies, no not for one Hundred Years purchaſe; which are now ſwallow'd up by the Uſurers, for oftentimes no more than16 or 18 Years Value.</p>
            <p>In the Eleventh Place, when the Landed Gentry, and others ſhall have Money at cheap Intereſt, near every Mans Home, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Titles are beſt known, and the Uſurers ſlothful Trade be out of practice; Theſe various, nay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Parties, will become united to the promoting of the common Good, ſo as that the firſt will be enabled, and (for their profit ſake) both will be forward, to aſſiſt in the retrievement of the <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi> and the carrying on that, and all other Trades to much higher degrees than ever; and when ſmall, or no Cuſtoms, or Exciſes ſhall be paid, ſave for ſuch Veſſels, or Goods as Reaſons of State ſhall require, Strangers Ships will be encouraged to make us frequent Viſits, and by ſuch freedom from charges, together with the happineſs of our Scituation, and the commodiouſneſs of our Harbours, <hi>England</hi> will naturally become the chief Store-houſe, and Bank of <hi>Europe,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Univerſe, and will be able to make a yet greater Figure in the World beyond preſent imagination; hold, and govern the Ballance of Chriſtendom more effectually, and prevent all ambitious Deſigns of an Univerſal Monarchy; and then will all neceſſaries be cheap to the Gentry, Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and poor, ſo as all the people of the Land will live much better and eaſier.</p>
            <p n="12">12. As Trade increaſes ſo will the Navigation to degrees beyond what can be at preſent foreſeen, which is ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proved by what goes before, that more need not be ſaid on this Subject.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33178:8"/>
            <p n="13">13. Whereas at preſent many Gentlemens Sons do but help to fill the Tables of Parents, Elder Brothers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Relations, and are oftentimes burthenſom Gueſts, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy in themſelves, and (tho againſt their wills) uſeleſs to their Countrey, and not ſeldom by their circumſtances ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to deſperate Courſes; If theſe Banks were eſtabliſh'd gentile Employments might be had, not only at the ſaid Banks, but in a multitude of profitable Enterpriſes which their Landed Friends and others, by Money to be had at low Intereſt, and at hand would be enabled, and Monied Men, (for the ſake of their own Advantages) would be induc'd to help them to good Poſts in; And ſo would the grievous Misfortunes of many ingenious young Gentlemen be remedied, and their Parents and Country made happy by them, who now either linger away their Lives, in tedious Miſery to themſelves, and charge to their Friends, or (forc'd on bad Practices) make igmominious Exits, to the perpetual Reproach of their Families.</p>
            <p n="14">14. When the Uſurers ſhall be put upon other Studies, to make profits of their Money, their Projections will be every where innumerable, and the Artificers, Labourers, and Poor, muſt be likewiſe call'd in to put all Undertakings in execution; which together with the Banks, will have occaſion for ſo many of both Sexes, as that Employments will want them, rather than they will lack Employments; which now is the ſad caſe of Thouſands in Cities and Countrey, to the very great charge of all Pariſhes in the Kingdom, and yet numbers are ſaid to be ſtarv'd, beſides thoſe that periſh by Famin in Priſons: The diſabled in their Hands may go on Errands, the lame in their other Limbs, may turn the Wheels of the Makers of Ropes, Cordage, Lines, twine Thred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo of Throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſo may the younger, that go not to School, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So as none other than the Superannuated, Impotent, and Infants will wane Proviſion.</p>
            <p>For the 15. Advantage, theſe Banks will procure the beſt Sales and prices for Cloth, and for all Productions and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33178:9"/>Native and Foreign, becauſe they'l ſell all Goods at beſt ſeaſons, and with leaſt charge, to the Clothiers and others, who by depoſiting Wares in any one Bank, until themſelves, or their Friends can make their beſt Markets, will have plenty of Money, (for ſmall Intereſts) to be paid them near Home, or afar off, where each Tradeſman ſhall chuſe to anſwer his occaſions, without being oblig'd to trifle away their Goods at low rates to get ready Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and to carry the ſame far and nigh, to obtain things uſeful for their reſpective Occupations; as now is the caſe with moſt of the Tradeſmen in <hi>England,</hi> to their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Charge, Hazard and Detriment.</p>
            <p>But if any other ſelfdeſigning Banks (under what Names Titles or diſguiſed Pretences ſoever) ſhall be tolerated to enjoy to themſelves the mighty profit by Uſury on the Nations Money; thoſe will be as prejudicial to the King and the Kingdom, as if the Goldſmiths and Scriveners ſtill had it, the caſe being alike to the Publick, whether the ſame be devoured by the one or the other: Nay the latter have the beſt Title to thoſe profits, becauſe 'tis the livelihood they are bred up in, which to ſuffer Bodies Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick to carry away from them whoſe Subſiſtance depends thereon, would ſeem Oppreſſion; and to permit 'em to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolize thoſe to themſelves, with excluſion of our Mother the Nation that ſupports us, would be very great Unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Undutifulneſs, and Ingratitude to her; Nay, why ſhe ſhould contentedly give any others the place, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave her ſelf of theſe prodigious Profits, which are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully her due; whilſt ſhe is in ſo very great want, and borrows on ſo very hard Terms of Uſury, is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable to Reaſon, or Juſtice to her ſelf.</p>
            <p>In fine, if the Parliament doubt of his Majeſties being punctually ſupplyed by this true ſort of National Banks, (alone by themſelves) yet if our Rulers ſhall but grant their eſtabliſhment, without leſſening at all, or omitting the leaſt part of the other Supplies already provided, the King by their help, may be the ſooner aſſiſted with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33178:9"/>to be paid in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or otherwhere aſſoon, and as much as his Majeſty himſelf, and the Parliament pleaſe, without exporting our own Caſh, at this exream Scarcity. And if theſe Banks may have leave to pay off the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms Debts, as faſt as they ſhall be able, the firſt years experience will undoubtedly raiſe their Reputation by acquitting the King and the Nation from payments of thoſe high Intereſts, that grate hard upon and conſume very much of their Treaſure, nay even of all Intereſts whatſoever, for thoſe Funds that are redeemable; and yet carry on the War with utmoſt Vigour, tho the charge ſhould hereafter exceed what the fame has hitherto been; The Senſe whereof, may ſo much diſcourage our Foes as to oblige them to ſubmit, and endeavour to purchaſe a ſpeedy Peace on ſuch Terms, as our King and his Friends, ſhall be pleaſed to admit them.</p>
            <p>The greatneſs of the Taxes, the difficulties to obtain Money, the dearneſs of Commodities, Domeſtick and Foreign, by reaſon of high Cuſtomes and Exciſes, lie hard upon the Nobility, Gentry, and all others, impoveriſh the Tradeſmen, hinder the Navigation, fill priſons, ſtarve the poor, and fupply Tiburn; All which Grievances, this moſt excellent healing true ſort of National Banks would (in one years time) redreſs to admiration, and put <hi>England</hi> into a glorious condition of proſperity for ever.</p>
            <p>But ſhall the landed Gentry, and other true Lovers of their King and Countrey, permit the vaſt profits of the Kingdom, on the Circulations of Paper payments (which by the way are unjuſtly ridicul'd) to devolve into the Cheſts of Bodies Politick, and other Uſurers; all thoſe will have great reaſon to unite together to ſtrengthen their Party, and the exorbitant profits will invite all Gaſhiers Receivers and other Dealers in Money, as alſo the rich Mony'd Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who may perſwade ſome of the very Members of Parliament themſelves to engage in their Fellowſhip, and will tempt them to exert their moſt vigorous Efforts, to influence all future Parliaments, (tho under ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts) to favour their intereſt, how ill ſoever the ſame
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33178:10"/>may comport with that of the good People of <hi>England</hi> in general, who (if this right honeſt ſort of National Banks be diſlik'd or delay'd) will languiſh under the Loſſes of near Six Millions of Money <hi>per Annum,</hi> or rather of much more, (as the ſame is computed to be) beſides infinite other very conſiderable Diſadvantages, than thoſe afore point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at.</p>
            <p>For 'tis more than probable, that our Neighbour Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, particularly our Brothers of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the ſame Conſtitution of Government, may ſee further and deeper into this matter, than we are at preſent willing to do; and may take occaſion, from this unhappy and willful Blindneſs in us, to erect the like Banks in thoſe Kingdoms; Whatſoever other Nations farther off, and free from our Comptrol (whoſe Governments will admit) may likewiſe do.</p>
            <p>By means whereof, we ſhall ſit ſtill, and envy the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits accruing to them, by improving their Trade and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, which they will draw away our people to help them to carry on the better, and wherein they may, in no long time, arrive to that height and perfection, as to decay and ſupplant our whole Traffick, and eclipſe the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation we have gain'd in the World, by the greatneſs and extent of our Commerce, to the weakning of our Naval Force, and endangering our Safety, which ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on our Walls of Wood, and the Superiority of our Shipping, to any other in the World.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Ireland</hi> it cannot be imagin'd, that ingenious people will any longer truckle and groan under the Drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery they now toil, of 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt, together with the difficulties of procuring Money in that Kingdom, where it is ſo very ſcarce, and hard to be obtain'd; beſides what other Advantages they may ſtrive to reach at.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Scotland,</hi> 'tis not to be expected that they who are (at this very Conjuncture) ſo ſolicitous in attempting a Trade to <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi> (never before by them adventur'd at) ſhould now neglect the getting before us; if poſſible,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33178:10"/>into methods ſo certain as theſe herein ſet forth, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that undertaking, and which will undoubtedly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on that and whatſoever reaſonable Enterpriſes, beſides, they ſhall take further in hand, to the inviting away of our Bulworks the Engliſh Seamen, and likewiſe multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of our Tradeſ-men, Artificers, and others, the moſt ingenious and induſtrious of our People, with no ſmall quantities of the Wealth and Treaſure of <hi>England,</hi> by ſuch tempting Encouragements as their Politicks may give, and by the ſoft, gentle, honeſt, and inoffenſive way's of Wiſedom and Reaſon, allure our pretious Traffick out of our Hands, which the Sword, and the Blood of <hi>England</hi> have ſo long labour'd to preſerve, againſt the Nations more Foreign, tearing it from us by force; whereby <hi>England</hi> will be impoveriſh'd; and we ſhall be juſtly upbraided of Supineneſs and Stupidity, when it may be too late for us ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, (if ever at all) to retrieve the unſpeakable Loſs of our dear Trade, through our obſtinate Blindneſs and wilful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſsneſs, to embrace this opportunity, of which Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath vouchſaf'd, the great kindneſs to give us the firſt offer; For if any Nation or Nations, that are altogether free from our Checks, ſhall inſiſt thereupon, whilſt we linger, our reſolute Deafneſs, may be for ever hereafter lamented, more than that of <hi>(now)</hi> beggarly <hi>Portugal,</hi> to their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged Countrey-man <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid that <hi>Scotland</hi> hath already ſo far advanced, as to have made (or are about to make) the Ports of that Kingdom free, which if ſo, that will menace the irrepairable Cataſtrophe of the prudent and ſoveraign conduct of K. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the VII. who refus'd the Match of his Daughter with <hi>France,</hi> and (to uſe his own words) did thereby eſchew ſending <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> but rather married her to <hi>Scotland,</hi> that he might bring <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> which wiſe Fore ſight of that King took effect, in King <hi>James</hi> the firſt of <hi>England;</hi> Now ſhall we neglect this Golden Opportunity of theſe National Banks, and <hi>Scotland</hi> lay hold on't before us? They will not (in likelyhood) fail to ſupplant and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33178:11"/>take from us the greateſt part of our Traffick, and alſo to become the Storehouſe and Bank of <hi>Europe, &amp;c.</hi> (which <hi>England</hi> hath now the firſt Refuſal to be, if it pleaſeth) and will ſoon thin our Rivers and Harbours of Shipping, and our Streets and Countrey of People; (eſpecially of the numerous Tradeſmen, and their Families) and in no long time draw <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and wherein the Benefits to <hi>Ireland,</hi> will oblige the no little Aſſiſtance of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>Divers other cogent and powerful Arguments might be treated of, which have not met with any material Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, unleſs Self-Intereſt is allow'd to be ſuch with its ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Prejudication, and therefore whatſoever Misfortunes, Miſeries, or Calamities ſhall befal <hi>England,</hi> through the want of theſe glorious National Banks, it may ſeem but reaſonable to impute the ſame, and value our ſelves owing therefore to the ſelf-ſeeking Uſurers of the Nation, and their coveteous and over-reaching Party, who will thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate themſelves no leſs Enemies to the King and the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> than is the <hi>French King;</hi> nay and in ſome Reſpects more pernicious.</p>
            <p>But on the other Hand, 'tis yet in our power (tho not like 'twill be ſo much longer) to anticipate all others, and to get the ſtart of all the World, and the Trades-people and Seamen of <hi>England,</hi> are ſo notedly known for their Ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity and Induſtry, and our Kingdom ſo happily ſcituated, and our Harbours ſo many and ſo very commodious, as that 'twill be in vain, for any People in the World to aim at the overtaking us in Trade, were we once gotten entred upon the right beſt methods thereof, which will leave no place at all for ſuſpecting the Authors being byaſs'd to any ſiniſter Self-Intereſt, (ſo much by him decried) unleſs the Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of his minute Participation in <hi>Communi Bono Regni An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae</hi> be ſo accompted, whatſoever his Labours, and Coſts have been, or ſhall be, having been hereto puſh'd on by the fervent Emotions of an Impulſe, purely to ſerve his Generation, whoſe glory thereby is the ſole end of his deſign.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33178:11"/>
            <p>Upon the whole, he hopes that the Title is much more than nakedly prov'd, if we haſten to eſtabliſh theſe admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Banks, for that all the profits on Uſury, and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations of Bank-Bills, will be converted entirely to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the King and the Kingdom, and ſo preſerve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the (already too much) impair'd Credit of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which will (inevitably and moſt certainly) be more exceedingly ſhockt, after the 4th. of <hi>May,</hi> if not ſeaſonably prevented by Wiſedom before hand; And by which means the King will be ſupplied more plentifully than ever, for carrying on the War with greateſt Vigour, the Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from paying ſo great Land Taxes, if any at all, and in a ſhort time diſcharged from great part, if not all, the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and Exciſes ſo burdenſom to the People; the Fiſhery, and divers laudable Undertakings be encouraged, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted to effect; all Perſons furniſh'd that ſhall have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with Money at 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt <hi>per Annum,</hi> near every Man's Home, and many large Advantages be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, other than thoſe ſpoken of in this Paper.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
